# M. Susan Schmidt, PhD Developmental & Technical Editor, Science Analyst, Environmental Educator

(252) 269-0032; <a href="mailto:susu@starfishnet.com">susu@starfishnet.com</a>; <a href="mailto:www.susanschmidt.net">www.susanschmidt.net</a>

### **Qualifications Summary**

Dr. Schmidt is an Editor and Educator with 30 years experience as university and secondary professor of literature, writing, and environmental communication and policy and 20 years as analyst and editor in government. She has broad knowledge of curriculum design, grant-writing, conflict resolution and mediation, media, stakeholder outreach, environmental laws and regulations. She is proficient in analysis of environmental impacts on water quality, wetlands and floodplains, endangered and threatened species, and historic properties. She can evaluate climate change, coastal zone consistency, migratory birds, public safety and health. She is fluent in French and German, functional in Spanish; has a NC Professional Educator's License, NC Environmental Educator, and US Coast Guard Captain's License.

### **Work History**

## Polish to Publish, Beaufort, NC Developmental Editor, January 2009 to Present

Advise authors on narrative structure; copyedit. Edited *The Beach Book* by Carl H. Hobbs (VIMS asst. director, Columbia UP): on waves, erosion, sea-level rise. Edited 4 novels, including *Light on Water* by C. L. Rawlins, a New Zealand Maori saga; 5 memoirs, including *Buzzard's Myth* by Alva Harris (who wrote 1972 EIS on Gulf oil-spill hazards). At national conferences, lead manuscript-editing, technical and creative-writing workshops. Lecturer for NC Humanities on ecological history and coastal issues. At Beaufort Art Center, produce contra-dance, teach creative-writing workshop & yoga. Boards: Carteret Local Food Network, NC Maritime Museum Jr. Sailing Program; Beaufort Strategic Planning Committee.

### **University Professor and High School Teacher 1973-2009**

Taught university technical and creative writing, science communication, conflict resolution, environmental policy & community planning, environmental literature & philosophy, science & religion at Carteret Community College 2001-2008 & 1979-83, Hampton University 2007, Brevard College 1996-2001, Warren Wilson College 1994-95, NC School of Science & Math (as UNC faculty) 1989-94, Duke University 1989-93, College of Charleston 1987-88, NC State University 1983, University of Virginia Engineering School 1979. Taught secondary literature, journalism, French, global environmental issues at Collegiate School in Richmond, VA 1973-76; Philips Academy in Andover, MA 1969 & 1989; SC Governor's School in Charleston 1988. Fellow at NEH Environmental Imagination Institute at Vassar, National Humanities Center, NC Center for Advancement of Teaching, Duke Environment & English.

### **Curriculum Designer, Grant-Writer 1976-2010**

Wrote grants topping \$4 million. Designed interdisciplinary curriculum for Stratford Hall on environmental history, Duke University on environmental philosophy for adults and 9<sup>th</sup>-graders, Christchurch School on experiential Chesapeake studies, Brevard College and NC School of Science & Math on environmental humanities, NC State University on humanities for engineering students, and Medical University of South Carolina on AIDS Education and on Medical Ethics for Family Doctors. Lighthouse study, Edenton Historical Commission. Received research grants from National Endowment for the Humanities to design interdisciplinary environmental-humanities curriculum, National Science Foundation on inter-basin water-transfer, Environmental Protection Agency on nonpoint-source-pollution runoff control, Office of Education for land-use/ water-quality workshops, American Association of University Women on Southern Appalachian native plants & traditional music, Fulbright Foundation to teach in West Germany, VA Center for Creative Arts to write in SW France, and NC Arts Council to research John Smith.

### Susan Schmidt- 2

## USDA Forest Service, Southern Research Station, Asheville, NC, and Atlanta, GA Contract Technical Editor & Workshop Trainer, August 1996 to December 2008

Edited scientists' journal articles and books, including *Deerskins And Cotton, Ecological Impacts of Historical Land Use in the Central Savannah River Area before 1950* by David White, (USDA Forest Service, 2008); *Ecology and Management of a Forested Landscape, Fifty Years on the Savannah River Site* (Island Press, 2005). Edited *Southern Appalachian Assessment* (Island Press, 1997). Led workshops (in grammar, style, logic, & law) training endangered-species biologists to write legally-defensible environmental-assessment documents. Led grant-writing workshops; edited symposia proceedings.

### Environmental Scientist/ Policy Analyst/ Editor/ Mediator, 1977-2001

For NC Natural Resources Leadership Institute, 1998-2000, mediated between NC Forest Resources & Natural Heritage to protect natural areas and wrote recreational-management plan for 12,000-acre DuPont State Forest. Mediated for Transylvania Dispute Settlement Center, Brevard, NC, 1997-2001. Edited Environmental Science Dictionary, Bruccoli Clark, 1988-91. As Virginia Sea Grant Editor, College of William & Mary, 1984-86, edited two monthly newsletters on commercial fishing and marine-science research. Edited San Diego Log (waterfront newspaper), 1984. As Environmental Scientist for NC Coastal Management, Morehead City, 1979-82, wrote policy reports and testified to Coastal Resources Commission on land use regulations to protect estuarine water quality, including wetland mitigation, coal ports, oil refineries; wrote grant proposal and management plan to establish NC Estuarine Research Reserve. For Nature Conservancy, wrote Carrot Island Preserve Management Plan, Beaufort, NC, 1979-83; wrote acquisition grant and management plan for Ivy Creek Natural Area, Charlottesville, VA, 1977-79. For US Department of Interior, Washington, 1977, reviewed environmental-impact statements on dams, mediated among departments, and wrote letter signed by Interior Secretary; wrote Executive-Order 11988 Guidelines on Floodplain Management.

### **Education**

Conflict-Resolution Fellow, Natural Resources Leadership Institute, NC State University, 1998-2000 Bioethics, Environmental Philosophy Fellow, Duke University Divinity School, 1990-93 PhD, American Literature, University of South Carolina, 1990 MA, Environmental Sciences, University of Virginia, 1980 Watershed ecology, water quality Botany study, Highlands (UNC), 1996, Mt. Lake (UVa) biology stations, 1976, 1990 MA, English, University of Virginia, 1972; Teaching License in English, Science (7-12<sup>th</sup> grades) BA, English, Connecticut College, May 1971; Oxford University, England, Honors 1969-70

#### **Publications**

Dr. Schmidt is the author of *Landfall Along the Chesapeake, in the Wake of Captain John Smith* (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2006) and gave 100 lectures on Chesapeake ecological history. She published 8 journal articles, 150 magazine/ newspaper articles, 7 literary essays, 8 poems, 5 books chapters. She edited 25 technical books, science reports & proceedings, 12 novels & memoirs.

### **Honors and Awards**

VA Center for Creative Arts Fellowship to write in SW France 2008

National Endowment for Humanities Fellowships 1993-94, 1997, AAUW 1999-2000

Most Influential Teacher of 2 highest graduates of NC State University 1994; 12 Brevard College graduates

Member: Coastal Society, Nat. Assoc. of Science Writers, Assoc. for Study of Literature & Environment

### **Recent Travel**

Walked 550 miles on Camino de Santiago in Spain and France, 2007-08. Trekked in New Zealand, Winters 2008 & 2010. Kenya Volunteer Conservation work winter 2011. Kayaked 500 miles in Alaska, kayaked 400 miles with Brevard students in NC & SC. Delivered sailboats to West Indies, 1980s.